<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The construction, and vse of the line of proportion By helpe whereof the hardest questions of arithmetique &amp; geometry, as well in broken as whole numbers, are resolved by addition and subtraction. By Edm: Wingate, gent.</title>
            <author>Wingate, Edmund, 1596-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2344</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2344)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1053:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The construction, and vse of the line of proportion By helpe whereof the hardest questions of arithmetique &amp; geometry, as well in broken as whole numbers, are resolved by addition and subtraction. By Edm: Wingate, gent.</title>
                  <author>Wingate, Edmund, 1596-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some pages marked, stained and torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mathematics --  Tables --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mathematical instruments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Line of Proportion</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a logarithmic number line</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>continuation of logarithmic number line</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>continuation of logarithmic number line</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONSTRVCTION, And Vſe of the Line of PROPORTION.</p>
            <p>By helpe whereof the hardes<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queſtions of <hi>Arithmetique</hi> &amp; <hi>Geometry,</hi> as well in broken as whole numbers, <hi>are reſolved by</hi> Addition <hi>and</hi> Subſtraction.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>EDM WINGATE,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Nulla dies ſine Linea.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Dawſon.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING not many moneths agoe publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed a diſcourſe, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the nature and vſe of the Logarithmeticall Tables, and obſerving the Table of Numbers there to be too ſmall for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary vſe, not giving indeed without much difficultie the Logarithme of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny number that exceeds 1000; I haue invented this tabular Scale, or <hi>Line of Proportion,</hi> by meanes whereof (as I take it) you ſhall find that defect fully ſupplyed: this Inſtrument yeelding you the reſolution of the hardeſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Arithmetique or Geometry, both in broken, and whole Numbers, onely by Addition and Subſtraction, when the terme required happens not to exceed 10000. although the termes propounded conſiſt of never ſo many places, as ſhall further appeare by the Treatiſe following.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:5"/>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>The Definition of the Line of Proportion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>The Deſcription and Vſe of the Scale of Logarithmes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. III. <hi>The Deſcription, Conſtruction, and Vſe of the Scale of Numbers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. IIII. <hi>The ioynt Vſe of the Scale of Numbers, and the Scale of Logarithmes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="mathematical_text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:5"/>
            <head>THE CONSTRVCTION, and Vſe of the Line of PROPORTION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Definition thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Line of Proportion is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſcale, broken off into tenne Fractions, vpon which the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithmes of numbers are found out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To vnderſtand the nature of Logarithmes, I referre you to Maſter <hi>Brigges</hi> his learned Worke, intituled <hi>Arithmetica Logarithmica,</hi> and to the Treatiſe mentioned in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Fraction is a tenth part of the Line of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, conſiſting of ſix Lines and fiue ſpaces;</hi> ſuch as are the parts <hi>a b c d,</hi> &amp; <hi>c d e f.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lines are thoſe, by which the ſpaces are diſtinguiſhed;</hi> So <hi>a b</hi> is the firſt, <hi>g h</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and <hi>c d</hi> the laſt line of the firſt Fraction,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2344:6"/>which <hi>c d</hi> is alſo the firſt line of <hi>c d e f</hi> the Fraction following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſpaces are the diſtances betwixt the lines; And they are either greater,</hi> as the firſt and laſt ſpaces of each fraction; <hi>or leſſe,</hi> ſuch as are the other three placed in the middeſt of each fraction.</p>
               <p>Theſe fractions, together with their Lines and ſpaces, muſt be vnderſtood to ioyne reſpectiuely one to another, in ſuch ſort that the whole <hi>Line of Proportion</hi> may be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be one intire and continued Line; As the left end of the firſt fraction, marked by the Letters <hi>a g c</hi> muſt be conceived to ioyne with the right end of the ſecond fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, noted by <hi>d f,</hi> and the left end of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond fraction, ſigned by <hi>c e,</hi> muſt be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to ioyne with the right end of the third Fraction, marked by <hi>f k;</hi> and ſo of the reſt: So that the whole <hi>Line of Proportion,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the right end of the firſt Fraction, marked by <hi>b h α d,</hi> and ending at the left end of the laſt Fraction, ſigned by <hi>l Ω m,</hi> muſt be conceived to be one intire Line, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A double ſcale, is when two ſeverall ſcales meete both vpon one common Line;</hi> So the <hi>Line of Proportion</hi> being compoſed of the two
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2344:6"/>ſcales, which meete vpon the fourth Line (marked at the beginning by α, and at the end by Ω) may fitly be called a double ſcale.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Deſcription and Vſe of the ſcale of</hi> Logarithmes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe ſcales, whereof the Line of Proportion conſiſts, are</hi> 1. <hi>the ſcale of</hi> Logarithmes, 2. <hi>the ſcale of</hi> Numbers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſcale of</hi> Logarithmes, <hi>is that deſcribed vnder the common Line</hi> α Ω; <hi>viz.</hi> in the two laſt ſpaces of the <hi>Line of Proportion,</hi> which are firſt divided into ten equall parts by the fractions themſelues (each fraction being the tenth part of the whole Line;) and theſe parts are ſigned at the right end of the fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the figures 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. and in the vſe of this ſcale for the finding of any number vpon it, are called <hi>thouſands:</hi> Againe, the ſame ſpaces are divided vpon each fraction (by croſſe lines ſtrucke through them) into ten other equall parts, which are likewiſe noted in the laſt ſpace of each fraction, at the beginning of each part
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2344:7"/>by the figures 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. and are hereafter called <hi>hundreds;</hi> then each of theſe hundreds is ſubdivided in the fourth ſpace of each fraction into ten other equall parts, which hereafter are termed <hi>tenths:</hi> Laſtly, each of thoſe tenths is againe ſuppoſed to be divided into ten parts, which are called <hi>vnits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vſe of this ſcale followes in the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the propoſition following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A number being given that exceedes not</hi> 10000, <hi>to finde it vpon the ſcale of</hi> Logarithmes.</p>
               <p>BEfore we come to the reſolution of this propoſition, it muſt be obſerved that the numbers propounded to be found vpon this ſcale, muſt alwayes conſiſt of foure places, being either ſignificant figures of ciphers, ſuch as are 2372. 2370. 2300. 2080. 2008. 2000. 0264. 0064. 0008. 0004. &amp;c. This being premiſed, you may finde any ſuch number vpon that ſcale by this direction following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Find the firſt figure of the number given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the thouſands,</hi> viz. <hi>the figures placed at the right end of the fractions; thou amongst the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2344:7"/>hundreds deſcribed vpon the fraction, vnto which that firſt figure directs you, ſearch the ſecond figure of the number given; againe, for the third figure count ſo many tenths, as that figure hath vnities; And for the laſt figure count ſo many vnits: This done the point of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Line</hi> α Ω, <hi>where the laſt figure happens to fall, is the point that repreſents the number gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example,</hi> 2 3 7 2 being given, I demand the point vpon the common Line, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the ſame number; 2 the firſt figure directs me to the third fraction, ſigned by the figure 2; 3 the ſecond figure leads me to the hundred, marked vpon that fraction by the figure 3; For 7. the third figure I count ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven tenths of that hundred, <hi>viz.</hi> to the point <hi>p;</hi> and for 2 the laſt figure I count two vnits of that tenth: which done, I find the number given to be repreſented vpon the third frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at the point <hi>n.</hi> So 2370. is repreſented at the point <hi>p;</hi> 2300. vpon the ſame fraction at the beginning of the hundred, ſigned by the figure 3; and 2000. at the beginning of the ſame fraction, the three cyphers follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 2. ſignifying that no hundreds, tenths, or vnits, are to be taken in finding the point, which repreſents that number: So likewiſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2344:8"/>2080. is found vpon the ſame fraction at the point <hi>q,</hi> the cypher in the ſecond place ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that no hundreds, and the other in the laſt place, that no vnits are to be taken in finding out that number vpon the ſcale: In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner 2008, is repreſented vpon the ſame frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the point <hi>r:</hi> And 0264. 0064. 0008. &amp; 0004. vpon the firſt fraction at the points <hi>s, t, u, x.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, by inverting the rules of this propoſition, any point of the common Line being given, you may find the number repreſented by it: So the points <hi>p n q r</hi> being given, the numbers repreſented by them are 2370. 2372. 2080. and 2008.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Deſcription, Conſtruction, and Vſe of the Scale of</hi> Numbers.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe ſcale of</hi> Numbers, <hi>is that deſcribed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouc the common Line</hi> α Ω, <hi>viz.</hi> in the three firſt ſpaces of the <hi>Line of Proportion,</hi> which are firſt divided into nine proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall parts (diſtinguiſhed by the great figures 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9.)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2344:8"/>the firſt beginning at the beginning of the Line noted by 1. and ending at the line that croſſeth thoſe three ſpaces vpon the fourth fraction, marked by the figure 2 on the right hand, and by a little cypher on the left: The ſecond beginning there, and ending at ſuch another croſſe Line vpon the fift fraction, ſigned by the figure 3: The third reaching from thence to another croſſe line vpon the ſeventh fractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, noted by the figure 4. In like manner, ſhall you finde the fift part to begin neere the left end of the ſeaventh fraction, the ſixt vpon the eight, the ſeaventh vpon the ninth, and the eight and nine parts vpon the laſt fraction, all ſigned by their proper figures 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. Which parts are hereafter called <hi>Primes,</hi> and are each of them againe divided into ten other parts, according to the ſame proportion, noted in the firſt ſpace of the Line by the little figures 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. (each of them having the Prime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure vnto which they belong annext re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely vnto them) which parts are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after called <hi>ſeconds,</hi> which <hi>ſeconds</hi> are each of them againe ſubdivided into ten other parts by croſſe Lines ſtrucke through the ſecond
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2344:9"/>and third ſpaces, and are hereafter termed <hi>thirds;</hi> which <hi>thirds</hi> are each of them againe divided, or at leaſt ſuppoſed to be divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ten parts, <hi>viz.</hi> the thirds contained in the firſt, ſecond, and third Primes, are really di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into ten parts; but thoſe betwixt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the fourth Prime, and the end of the Line, are onely divided into two parts, and therefore each of thoſe parts are concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to haue the value of fiue, which ten parts of the thirds are hereafter called <hi>fourths:</hi> Laſtly, each <hi>fourth</hi> in the firſt ſecond &amp; third Primes is conceived to be againe divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ten parts, which are hereafter termed <hi>fifts.</hi> Now the conſtruction of this ſcale is in this manner:</p>
               <p>Repaire vnto M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Brigges</hi> his Tables of <hi>Logarithmes,</hi> and ſuppoſing 1000. to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented at the beginning of the <hi>Line of Proportion,</hi> finde in thoſe Tables the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithme of 1001. which is 3,00042, 40774, 7932, whereof take onely 3,0004, the firſt fiue figures; then caſting away 3 the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſtique (his office being onely to ſhew of how many places the number, vnto which the Logarithme belongs, conſiſts, as I haue formerly ſhewed in the Treatiſe aboue-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) find by the propoſition of the laſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2344:9"/>chapter vpon the ſcale of <hi>Logarithmes</hi> 0004, the figures that remaine, which are repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon the firſt Fraction at the point <hi>x;</hi> this done, iuſt againſt that point in the ſcale of <hi>Numbers</hi> marke the point <hi>z,</hi> which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the number 1001 vpon that ſcale, then taking the Logarithme of 1002. doe in like manner, and ſo proceede till you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed all the diviſions of the ſcale of <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> vpon the Line.</p>
               <p>The vſe of this ſcale appeares in the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the propoſitions following.</p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROPOSITION I. <hi>A whole number being given to finde it vpon the ſcale of Numbers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FInde the firſt figure of the number given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Primes of that ſcale; then find the ſecond figure amongſt the ſeconds of that Prime;</hi> 3. <hi>for the third figure count ſo many thirds of that ſecond;</hi> 4. <hi>for the fourth count ſo many fourths of that third; and laſtly, if the number fall in the firſt, ſecond, or third Prime, for the fift figure count ſo many fifts of the laſt fourth: this done, the point, where the laſt figure falls vpon the common Line</hi> α Ω, <hi>is the point that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the number given.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2344:10"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Example,</hi> 17268. being given, I demand the point vpon the common Line, where it is repreſented: 1. the firſt figure directs me to the firſt <hi>Prime,</hi> and 7. to the ſeaventh <hi>ſecond</hi> of that Prime, placed vpon the third fraction at the little figures 71. then for 2 I count two <hi>thirds</hi> of that ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> to the point μ, and for 6 I count ſix <hi>fourths</hi> of that third, that is, to the point ν; And laſt of all for 8 the laſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, I take eight <hi>fifts</hi> of that fourth, ſo that I find 17268. the number given to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at the point ε vpon the third fraction; So 1726. or 17260. is found at the point ν; 172, 1720, or 17200. at the point μ; 17, 170, 1700, or 17000 at the ſeaventh <hi>ſecond</hi> of the firſt Prime, 1. 10. 100. 1000. &amp;c. at the beginning of the Line; And 2. 20. 200. 2000. &amp;c. at the beginning of the ſecond <hi>Prime:</hi> In like manner 2040. is repreſented at the point φ vpon the fourth fraction, the cypher in the ſecond place ſignifying that no <hi>ſeconds,</hi> and the other in the fourth or laſt place, ſhewing that no <hi>fourths</hi> are to be taken in finding out that number vpon the ſcale: So likewiſe 2008, is repreſented vpon the ſame fraction at the point ψ, the cyphers in the ſecond and third places ſhewing that no <hi>ſeconds</hi> or <hi>thirds</hi> are to be taken in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of that number.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2344:10"/>
                  <p> Contrariwiſe, by changing the rules of this propoſition, any point of the common Line being given, you may find the number repreſented by it, ſo the points ε vpon the third fraction, and ψ vpon the fourth, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the numbers 17268. &amp; 2008.</p>
                  <p>From the premiſſes ariſetheſe corrollaries.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>A number that conſiſts of more figures then fiue, and falls in the firſt, ſecond, or third Prime, is repreſented at the point where the fift figure falls:</hi> So 17268347. is repreſented vpon the third fraction at the points, and 20080372. vpon the fourth at the p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nt ψ.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>A number that conſiſts of more figures then foure, and falls betweene the beginning of the fourth Prime, and the end of the Line, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented at the point, where the fourth figure falls:</hi> So 4236, and 4236873. are both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented vpon the ſeaventh fraction at the point θ.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>A point of the common Line in the firſt, ſecond, or third Prime, alwayes giues you a number, that conſiſts of fine places;</hi> So the points <hi>ε, ν,</hi> &amp; μ being given, the numbers repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them are 17268, 17260 &amp; 17200.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>A point of the common Line betweene the beginning of the fourth Prime, and the end of the Line, alwayes yeelds you a number compoſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2344:11"/>of foure places:</hi> So θ, and χ vpon the ſeaventh fraction repreſent 4236, and 4230.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP: 2. <hi>A broken number being given to finde it vpon the ſcale of Numbers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PRefixe the whole parts of the number given before the numerator of the fraction, and thereby make them as it were one intire num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; then by the propoſition aforegoing finde the point which repreſents that number, which alſo will be the point, that repreſents the broken number propounded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example,</hi> 172 68 / 100 being given, 172 being prefixed before 68, the numerator of the fraction, conſtitutes the whole nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber 17268, which by the propoſition aforegoing is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the third fraction at the point <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: So 17.26, that is 17 26 / 100, and 1. 726, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 726 / 1000 are both repreſented vpon the ſame fraction at the point ν; in like manner 20.40. and 20.08. are found vpon the fourth fraction at the points φ, and ψ.</p>
                  <p>But here it is to be obſerved, that the frac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the broken numbers propounded to be found vpon this ſcale, muſt alwayes haue for their denominator a number conſiſting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2344:11"/>of an vnit in the firſt place towards the left hand, and nothing but cyphers towards the right, ſuch as are 10. 100. 1000. 10000. &amp;c. And if the fractions of the broken numbers given be not ſuch, they ought to be reduced to fractions of that kinde.</p>
                  <p>Now other fractions are reduced to fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that kind for the moſt part vpon view, as if the number given were 12. foote, and 9. inches, that number being reduced is 12.75. <hi>viz.</hi> 12 75 / 100; and 12. pounds 14 ſhillings after reduction is 12.7, that is 12 1 / 10. But when you meete with a broken number, whoſe fraction is not reduccable vpon view, it may be reduced by the rule of three; for as the denominator of the fraction given is to 10. 100. or 1000. &amp;c. ſo is the numerator of the ſame fraction to the numerator of the fraction required: So 17 98 / 305, that is, 17 yeares, and 98 dayes being given, the proportion will be;</p>
                  <p>As 365 to 1000: So 98 to 268.</p>
                  <p>So that 1000 being the denominator, and 268 the numerator of the fraction required, your number after reduction will ſtand thus 17 268 / 1000, or thus 17.268. Now to find 268. the fourth proportionall by the helpe of the Logarithmes, I referre you to the third Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2344:12"/>of the fift chapter of my booke aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned: But in this caſe let the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator of the fraction required alwayes exceed the denominator of the fraction given, as in the example aforegoing 1000 exceeds 365.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>The ioynt Vſe of the ſcale of Numbers, and the ſcale of Logarithmes together.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP. I. <hi>A whole number being given to find the Logarithme therof.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FInde vpon the ſcale of Numbers, by the firſt propoſition of the laſt chapter the point that repreſents the number given, then by the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the ſecond chapter obſerue vpon the ſcale of Logarithmes the number repreſented by that point; this done, if you prefixe before that number his proper Characteriſtique, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire number is the Logarithme required.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Characteriſtique is the firſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Logarithme, conſiſting of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnities within one, as the number, vnto which that Logarithme belongs, conſiſts of places: So the Characteriſtique of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2344:12"/>betwixt 1, and 10 is 0; betwixt 10, and 100 is 1; betwixt 100, and 1000 is 2; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt 1000, and 10000 is 3, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example,</hi> 17268 being given, I demand his Logarithme, by the firſt propoſition of the laſt Chapter I find 17268 vpon the third fraction at the point <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which giues me vpon the ſcale of Logarithmes by the propoſition of the ſecond chapter the number 2372, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which, becauſe the number given con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of fiue places, I prefixe foure, ſo that the intire Logarithme of 17268 the number gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is 42372: So the Logarithme of 2040 is 33096; and the Logarithme of 2008 is 33028, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP. 2. <hi>A broken number being giuen, to find the Logarithme therof.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FInde vpon the ſcale of Numbers by the laſt propoſition of the laſt chapter the point that repreſents the number given; then by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſecond chapter take vpon the ſcale of Logarithmes the number repreſented by that point; this done, if you place before that number his proper Characteriſtique, that is, a figure conſiſting of ſo many vnities, ſaue one, as the whole parts of the number given conſiſts of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2344:13"/>that intire number is that you looke for.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example,</hi> 172. 68 being given, I demand his Logariſme, that number is found by the laſt propoſition of the laſt chapter vpon the third fraction at the point <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which yeelds you vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcale of Logarithmes by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſecond chapter the number 2372; And now becauſe 172 (being the whole parts of the number given) conſiſts of three places, prefixe before 2372 the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractcriſtique 2; which done, the intire Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithme of 172.68 will be found 22372: ſo the Logarithme of 17.26 is 12370, and the Logarithme of 1.726 is 02370.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>PROP. 3. <hi>A Logarithme being given to find the number vnto which it belongs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NEglecting the Characteriſtique of the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithme given, find by the propoſition of the ſecond chapter the point where the other fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures thereof are repreſented vpon the ſcale of Logarithmes, then by the firſt propoſition of the laſt chapter take off vpon the ſcale of Numbers the number repreſented by that point; this done, obſerving of how many vnities the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſtique of the Logarithme given conſiſts,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2344:13"/>take one more of the firſt figures, that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber taken vpon the ſcale of nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers hath towards the left hand, as if the Characteriſtique be</hi> 0, <hi>take one of thoſe figures, if it be</hi> 1, <hi>take two, if</hi> 2, <hi>take three, &amp;c. which figures will be the whole parts of the number required, and if there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine any figures towards the right hand, they are the numerator of a Fraction, whoſe deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minator is a number conſiſting of an vnitie in the firſt place towards the left hand, and of ſo many cyphers towards the right, as there are figures remaining, which fraction is the broken parts of the number demanded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example;</hi> The Logarithme 42372 being given, I demand the number vnto which it belongs; 2372 the other figures beſides 4 the Characteriſtique I finde by the prop of the 2. chap. to be repreſented in the ſcale of Logarithmes vpon the third Fraction at the point <hi>n,</hi> at which point vpon the ſcale of Numbers I find by the 1 prop. of the laſt ch. to be repreſented the number 17268; and now becauſe the Characteriſtique of the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithme given is 4 the whole nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber 17268 is the number, vnto which the Logarithme given appertaines, but if the Logar. given were 22372, his number would be 172.68; the Charact. 2 ſhewing that 172 the three
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2344:14"/>firſt figures of the number found ought to be taken for the whole parts, and 68 for the fraction of the number, vnto which that Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithme belongs.</p>
                  <p>From this Propoſition ariſe theſe Corral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>When a Logarithme, whoſe Charact. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds</hi> 4, <hi>falls within the firſt, ſecond, or third Prime, the firſt fiue figures of the number, vnto which it belongs, can onely be knowne;</hi> So if the Logarithine given were 72372, the fiue firſt figures of the number, vnto which it belongs are 17268.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>When a Logarithme, whoſe Charact. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes</hi> 3 <hi>happens to fall betwixt the beginning of the fourth Prime and the end of the Line, the firſt foure figures of the number, vnto which it belongs, are onely diſcoverable vpon the Line:</hi> So the Logarithme 76270 being given, the foure firſt figures of the number, vnto which it belongs, are 4236, which you ſhall finde repreſented vpon the ſeaventh fraction at the point θ.</p>
                  <p>But now in taking the numbers vpon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſcales obſerue this rule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When you haue directed your eye vnto a point vpon the common Line in taking a n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mber vpon either of the ſcales, firſt take the leaſt parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2344:14"/>by that point, and then the reſt in the ſame order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As in the Example of the laſt propoſition, the Logarithme 42372 being propounded, your eye is directed by it vpon the ſcale of Logarithmes vnto the point <hi>n;</hi> and therefore in remooving your view for taking vpon the ſcale of Numbers the number, vnto which that Logarithme belongs, firſt take the filts, <hi>viz.</hi> 8, then 6 the fourths, and ſo the reſt in order; which done, carrying in you minde, eight, ſixe, two, ſeaven, one, and beginning with 8 firſt, ſet them downe thus, 17268, as before.</p>
                  <p>In like manner, in the example of the 1. Prop. of this ch. the number 17268, being given, your eye is directed vpon the ſcale of Numbers vnto the point <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; and therefore in remooving your view for taking vpon the ſcale of Logarithmes the Logarithme of that number, firſt obſerue the vnits, <hi>viz.</hi> 2, then 7 the tenths, and ſo the reſt in order; this done, keeping in your minde the figures ſo taken, ſet them downe as before, thus, 2372. And in obſerving this Rule, after a little practice, you ſhall finde much eaſe, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2344:15"/>
                  <p> Thus having ſhewed you how to find vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Line of Proportion</hi> the number of any Logarithme, and the Logarithme of any number propounded vnder the ſeverall limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the rules aforegoing; for the vſe of the Logarithmes being found, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you to the Treatiſes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned at the beginning of this Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2344:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
